(
"ai_sub_version": "3.3.0",
"generated_at": "2026-07-21T01:33:37.917909",
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.1-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
愛のネタバレ「別れ」っぽいな
Spoiler warning for romance: it's heartbreak core.
人生のネタバレ「死ぬ」っぽいな
Spoiler warning for existence: it's grave core.
なにそれ意味深でかっこいいじゃん...
Isn't that so meaningful and cool?
それっぽい単語集で踊ってんだ
Dancing to a collection of plausible words.
失敬
Excuse me.
とぅ とぅる とぅ とぅ とぅる 風
Tu-turu tu tu-turu style...
ぽいじゃん ぽいじゃん
Seems like it, seems like it!
とぅ とぅる とぅ とぅ とぅる 風
Tu-turu tu tu-turu style...
とぅ とぅる とぅ とぅ とぅる
Tu-turu tu tu-turu...
神っぽいな
It's so god-ish.
もういいぜ もういいぜ それ
I've had enough, I've had enough of that.
もういいぜ もういいぜ
I've had enough, I've had enough.
逆に興奮してきたなぁ
Actually, I'm starting to get excited.
おっきいね おっきいね 夢
So big, so big, your dream.
おっきいね おっきいね
So big, so big.
景気いいけど 品性はthe end
Prosperous, but your class is at its end.
うええい うええい
Woo-hoo, woo-hoo!
"Gott ist tot"
“Gott ist tot.”
神っぽいな それ 卑怯
Isn't that god-ish? How unfair.
神っぽいな それ "My God"
Isn't that god-ish? “My God!”
アイウォンチュー ウォンチュー
I want you, want you.
IQが下がっていく感じ
With a feeling of my IQ dropping.
邪心っぽいな それ 畢竟
That seems so malicious after all.
邪心っぽいな それ "My God"
That seems so malicious, “My God!”
アイヘイチュー ヘイチュー
I hate you, hate you.
害虫はどっち
Which one of us is the pest?
その髪型 その目 その口元
That hairstyle, those eyes, that mouth.
その香水 その服 そのメイク
That perfume, those clothes, that makeup.
あれっぽいな それ 比況
That seems like “that,” a metaphor.
あれっぽいな それ
That seems like “that.”
その名言 その意見 その批評
That quote, that opinion, that critique.
そのカリスマ そのギャグ そのセンス
That charisma, that joke, that sense.
神っぽいな それ 卑怯
Isn't that god-ish? How unfair.
ぽいな ぽいな ぽい
Seems like it, seems like it, seems like it.
憧れちゃう！
I'm falling for it!
とぅ とぅる とぅ とぅ とぅる 風
Tu-turu tu tu-turu style...
ぽいじゃん ぽいじゃん
Seems like it, seems like it!
とぅ とぅる とぅ とぅ とぅる 風
Tu-turu tu tu-turu style...
とぅ とぅる とぅ とぅ とぅる
Tu-turu tu tu-turu...
神っぽいな
It's so god-ish.
メタ思考する本質は悪意
The essence of meta-thinking is malice.
人を小馬鹿にしたような作為
Deeds that look down on others.
無為に生き延びるのは難しい
Living idly is hard to do.
権力に飲まれて揺らぐ灯り
A flickering light swallowed by power.
神を否定し神に成り代わり
Denying God, taking God's place.
玉座で豹変する小物達
The small fry changing colors on the throne.
批判に見せかけ自戒的祈り
Self-admonishing prayers disguised as critique.
Do you know 何言ってるの
Do you know what you are saying?
何言ってるの それ
What are you even saying?
意味がよくわかんないし
I don't really get it anyway.
眠っちゃうよ マジ
I'm seriously about to fall asleep.
飽きっぽいんだ オーケー
I get bored easily, okay?
踊れるやつ ちっちゃいね 器
Those who can dance have tiny capacities.
天才ゆえ孤独ですね
A genius, hence lonely, right?
Gott ist tot
“Gott ist tot.”
神っぽいな それ 卑怯
Isn't that god-ish? How unfair.
神っぽいな それ "My God"
Isn't that god-ish? “My God!”
超健康 健康 言い張って
Insisting you're ultra healthy, healthy.
くたばっていく感じ
Then dropping dead anyway.
ヤケっぽいな それ 畢竟
That seems so desperate after all.
ヤケっぽいな それ "My God"
That seems so desperate, “My God!”
もう哀愁 哀愁
Nothing but sorrow, sorrow.
そのタイトル その絵 その音楽
That title, that art, that music.
その歌 あれっぽいな それ 比況
That song seems like “that,” a metaphor.
あれっぽいな それ
That seems like “that.”
その名言 その意見 その批評
That quote, that opinion, that critique.
そのカリスマ そのギャグ そのセンス
That charisma, that joke, that sense.
神っぽいな それ 卑怯
Isn't that god-ish? How unfair.
ぽいな ぽいな ぽい
Seems like it, seems like it, seems like it.
憧れちゃうわ！
I'm falling for it!
愛のネタバレ「別れ」っぽいな
Spoiler warning for romance: it's heartbreak core.
人生のネタバレ「死ぬ」っぽいな
Spoiler warning for existence: it's grave core.
すべて理解して wazuratta
Soon I saw it all for what it was and I cried.
無邪気に踊っていたかった
I had only wished to dance without a reason why.
ストレート
Straight
ドキドキする
Heart racing
視線はまるで
Your gaze is just like...
レーザービーム
...a laser beam
心をシュワりと
Going right through...
突き刺すの
...my heart
虹色の
A rainbow...
ラブビーム
...love beam
実る果実が
A ripening fruit...
水を弾いて
...repels water
キラキラしてる
Like a glittering...
光に似てる
...light
グラウンドに立つ
Standing on the field...
キミの姿が
...your radiant figure
まぶしくて 少し照れちゃうけど
It makes me feel a little shy
ストレート
Straight
まっすぐだね
...direct
恋愛はきっと
Love is surely...
レーザービーム
...a laser beam
心をシュワりと
Going right through...
突き刺すの
...my heart
虹色の
A rainbow...
ラブビーム
...love beam
ふたりを繋ぐ
Connecting the two of us...
秘密の光
...a secret light
あの日見つけた
Found that day...
秘密の光
...a secret light
恋の瞬間
A moment of love...
音は止まって
...sound pauses
時間はスローリーに
Time goes slowly...
恋の光線
...a love beam
ストレート
Straight
ドキドキする
Heart racing
視線はまるで
Your gaze is just like...
レーザービーム
...a laser beam
心をシュワりと
Going right through...
突き刺すの
...my heart
虹色の
A rainbow...
ラブビーム
...love beam
ストレート
Straight
まっすぐだね
...direct
恋愛はきっと
Love is surely...
レーザービーム
...a laser beam
心をシュワりと
Going right through...
突き刺すの
...my heart
虹色の
A rainbow...
ラブビーム
...love beam
よぉ〜〜〜〜っ
Yooo~
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Come one, come all, take a look!
始まりました！ らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ！
It's started! Raden's new outfit 3D reveal live!
今宵はまだまだこれから！ 皆さん、一緒に盛り上がっていきましょう！
Tonight is just getting started! Everyone, let's hype it up together!
尽きない 好奇心
Endless curiosity,
素晴らしきジャポニズムに触れて
touching upon wonderful Japonism.
令 和の 風雲児
The soldier of fortune of the Reiwa era,
皆々にお届けいたしましょう
I shall deliver it to everyone!
饒舌に 情熱
Loquaciously, with passion,
伝えたい愛に溢れている
overflowing with the love I want to convey.
無知の 知がきっと
The "knowledge of ignorance" will surely...
素敵な始まりになるんだよ
...become a wonderful beginning.
知って
Know...
欲しい
...I want you to know.
たらふく味わって
Taste it to your heart's content.
尊い
Precious...
人生
...life.
紐解いた 歴史に
Untangling history...
心惹かれていく
...I find myself captivated.
遥か遠く 電波に乗って あなたまで
Riding the airwaves to you, far, far away...
この想い 純粋に 伝えたい
...I want to convey these feelings purely.
新しい世界
A new world...
見せてあげる
...I will show you.
開口一番 やっちゃって
Opening statement, just do it!
破天荒に 型破って
Unprecedentedly breaking the mold,
打ち立てる 金字塔
establishing a monumental achievement.
パンチライン 時を超え
Punchline transcending time,
出囃子に 乗せて
riding on the theatrical entrance music.
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Come one, come all, take a look!
はい、はい！
Hi, Hi!
はい！
Hi!
はい、はい！
Hi, Hi!
はい！
Hi!
浪漫を抱いた人生を 丸ごと賭けて傾きましょ
With a life full of romance, let's bet it all and be wild!
刹那に生きた足跡を 偉大な先人と共に
Leaving footprints of living in the moment, together with great pioneers.
洒落た口火切って 手招く芸事の深淵
Sparking a stylish start, beckoned into the depths of the arts.
相反する感情 愛憎超えていく感動
Conflicting emotions, moving beyond love and hate into inspiration.
遥か遠く世界超え 宇宙まで
To the far reaches, beyond the world, even to space!
この想い果てしなく届けたい
I want to deliver this feeling without end!
オリエンタル オクシデンタル
Oriental, Occidental...
どちらも愛しちゃって
...loving them both.
掻き立てる衝動が加速する
The driving impulse accelerates.
創造の世界へと飛び込んで
Plunging into a world of creation,
小噺に乗せて
...riding on a short comic story!
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Roll up, roll up, come and see!
語り継いでいく 一世の想い
Passing down the feelings of a lifetime...
あなたの心に寄り添って
...staying close to your heart.
道楽主義で 小粋にいなせ
With a pleasure-seeking spirit, stylish and chic...
そんな生き様 如何ですか？
...how do you like this way of life?
遥か遠く電波に乗ってあなたまで
Riding the radio waves, far away to you,
この想い純粋に伝えたい
...I want to convey this feeling purely!
新しい世界見せてあげる
I'll show you a new world!
開口一番 やっちゃんて
Right from the opening line, let's do it!
破天荒に型破って打ち立てる
Breaking the mold in an unprecedented way, establishing...
金字塔 パンチライン 時を超え
...a monumental achievement, a punchline that transcends time.
出囃子に乗せて
Riding on the stage-entrance music...
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
...roll up, roll up, come and see!
寄ってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい！
Roll up, roll up, come and see!
はい、はい！
Hi, hi!
はい！
Hi!
はい、はい！
Hi, hi!
はい！ということで、ということで…
Yes! And with that, with that...
始まりました！
...it has begun!
らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ！
Raden's New Outfit Reveal 3D Live!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much!
はい、皆様改めまして、こんばんは！
Yes, once again, everyone, good evening!
ホロライブデバイス ReGLOSSの、美術・美術のミュージアムプリンセス担当…
From Hololive DEV_IS ReGLOSS, in charge of art and museum princess...
儒烏風亭らでんは前座見習い…
...Juufuutei Raden, the opening act apprentice...
ちょっと待って
Wait a minute.
儒烏風亭らでんでございます！
I am Juufuutei Raden!
みんな来てくれてありがとうございます！
Thank you all for coming!
本日のハッシュタグは、ハッシュタグ「#らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ」で…
Today's hashtag is #らでん新衣装お披露目3Dライブ...
いっぱいポストしてくれると、とても嬉しいです。よろしくお願いします！
...and I'd be very happy if you posted a lot with it! Thank you!
「ちょっとらでん大丈夫？」って言われてます。
People are asking, "Is Raden okay?"
大丈夫です、ありがとうございます！
I'm fine, thank you!
さあ今回ね、らでん3Dお披露目…
Well, this time, Raden's 3D reveal...
新衣装お披露目ライブ…ミラクル重大発表祭り！
...New Outfit Reveal Live Miracle Major Announcement Festival!
タイトルにもある通り、何やら重大発表が…
As the title says, there are some major announcements...
あるとか、ないとか。しかも…
...or maybe not. And...
1つだけじゃないの！
...it's not just one!
ということで、今日はぜひ最後まで…
So, please make sure to...
お楽しみください！
...enjoy until the very end today!
さあそして皆様、気になってますよね。
Now, everyone, you must be curious.
この新衣装、いかがですか？
How do you like this new outfit?
ドゥンドゥンドゥンドゥン…
*drumroll*
どう？みんな、どうかな？
How is it? What does everyone think?
これがわたくし、らでんの新衣装…
This is my new outfit...
ミュージアムプリンセス衣装でーす！
...the Museum Princess outfit!
どう？
How is it?
どうかな？どうかな？
What do you think? What do you think?
ちょっとね、今日ね、コメントのラグがあって、あれなんですけれども。
Well, today there's a bit of lag in the comments, so it is what it is, but...
あ、良い？「良い」？
Oh, nice? "Nice"?
ありがとう！ありがとうございます！
Thank you! Thank you very much!
「可愛い」？ありがとう！ありがとうございます！
"Cute"? Thank you! Thank you very much!
え、今回ですね、100万人記念ということで、
And this time, in commemoration of reaching 1 million subscribers,
さくらしおり先生にお仕立ていただきましたー！
...it was designed by Sakura Shiori-sensei!
イェーイ！
Yay!
これもね、普段から応援してくださっている皆様のおかげです。
This is also thanks to everyone who always supports me.
本当にありがとう！ありがとうございます！
Thank you so much! Thank you very much!
もちろんね、このライブの後、
And of course, after this live,
アンコールライブっていうのがメンバーシップ限定であるんですけれども、
...there will be an encore live exclusive to membership,
そこでまたのんびりとこのお衣装について詳しくね、
...where we will look at this outfit in more detail and at a relaxed pace,
見ていきたいと思いますので、気になるよって方は…
...so if you are interested...
メンバーシップの方に加入していただければと思います。
I hope you'll consider joining my membership!
今日ね、お昼くらいにメンバーの方が使えるスタンプが追加されましたので、
Today around noon, we added some stamps that members can use,
ぜひコメント欄で、よかったら使ってみてください。
so please try using them in the chat if you'd like.
もうみんな使いたくてたまらない、アロワナスタンプとかが追加されてるんで、
We've added an arowana stamp that everyone has been dying to use!
ぜひ皆さんね、コメント欄いっぱいアロワナを泳がせてください。
So please make lots of arowanas swim in the chat!
よろしくお願いします。
Thank you very much!
さあということで、お衣装、改めて新衣装なんですが、
So, once again, about this new outfit...
今回衣装のほかに、ちょっとね、ひとつ、とあるものを作りましたよ。
Beside the outfit itself, I actually had one special item made!
楽曲中にもね、出てきたんですけれども、
It also appeared during the song earlier, but...
じゃんじゃかじゃんじゃんじゃん、あ、逆！じゃーん！
Ta-da! Ah, other way... Ta-da!
ステッキでございます！
It's a cane!
いいでしょう、これ？かっこいいでしょう？
Isn't it great? It looks so cool, right?
今回ね、特注でステッキ、作っちゃったー！
I had this cane custom-made for this occasion!
しかも！これだけじゃないんですよ。
And that's not all!
見ててね。
Watch closely.
らでんビーム！
Raden Beam!
うわー！レーザービームだ！すごい！
Wow! It's a laser beam! Incredible!
今回ね、あの、レーザービームを出せるようにしてもらいました。
This time, I asked them to make it shoot a laser beam.
ヴン ヴン ヴン ヴン...
Vroom, vroom, vroom, vroom...
もう大丈夫です。疲れちゃう。
Okay, that's enough. I'll get tired.
いや、もう今日はね、ライブまだまだこれからですので、体力は温存していかないと。
No, the live show has just started today, so I need to save my energy.
でも今日は、自分の体力がもう空っぽになるまで、
But today, I'm going to perform with everything I've got
全力でライブするから、みんな応援よろしくね！
until my stamina is completely empty! Please cheer me on!
それでは、そろそろ、次の曲にいきたいと思います。
Now, I think it's about time to move on to the next song.
さあ次の曲はなんなのか、重大発表とはなんなのか、ワクワクしながら聞いてくださいね。
I wonder what the next song is, and what the major announcement is? Please listen with excitement!
そしてここからはゲストも登場します！
And we also have guests appearing from here on!
ゲストパートは収録になりますので、あしからず。
Please note that the guest part is pre-recorded.
それでは、今宵はまだまだ始まったばかり。みんなで一緒に楽しみましょう！
Now, tonight has only just begun. Let's all have fun together!
それでは、どうぞ！
So, here we go!
そう高く 果てなく
So high, endlessly,
明日へと導くよ
it will guide us to tomorrow.
私だけの光放ちたい
I want to shine my own unique light.
DIVE!
Wow...
自信なくしただ
Losing confidence,
心に鍵かけて
I just lock up my heart,
響く自分の声に
plugging my ears to the echo
耳塞いでた
of my own voice.
本当はいつだって
The truth is, I always knew
わかっていたんだよ
deep down...
一番大切なもの
...that the most important thing
ここにあること
is right here.
無限に広がる宇宙(そら)
In this infinitely spreading sky,
迷わず進もう
let's move forward without hesitation.
Go Fly! Go Fly!
Yes, So High!
目を閉じて
Even if I close my eyes
言い聞かせてみたってもう
and try to convince myself,
体中騒いでる
my whole body is racing,
止まらない鼓動強く
my unstoppable heartbeat growing stronger.
そう高く 果てなく
So high, endlessly,
抱きしめた未来が
the future we embraced
奇跡になる
will become a miracle.
生まれた思いが
The feelings that were born
明日へと導くよ
will guide us to tomorrow.
私だけの光放ちたい
I want to shine my own unique light.
DIVE!
Wow...
誰のものでもない
Belonging to no one else,
心に問いかけて
I question my heart,
選んだ道の先へと
heading straight towards the end
まっすぐに
of the path I chose.
どんな時だって
No matter when,
見失わないよ
I won't lose sight of it,
一番大切な場所を
because I found
見つけたから
the most important place.
遠回りでもいい
Even if it's a detour, it's fine.
胸張って進もう
Let's march forward with our heads held high.
Louder! Louder!
Sing Louder!
不器用かな
Maybe I'm clumsy,
でも傷ついたって構わないよ
but I don't care if I get hurt.
曇りない気持ちで
With cloudless feelings,
生きたいプライド私らしく
I want to live my pride as myself.
両手を広げて
Spreading both hands wide,
解き放った昨日が
the yesterday we released
翼になる
will become wings.
重ねた出会いが
The encounters we layered together...
この時 色づくよ
At this moment, it gains color.
私だけの光 信じて
Believing in my own unique light...
DIVE!
そう 高く
Yes, higher...
果てなく
...and endlessly,
抱きしめた未来が
the future we embraced...
奇跡になる
...will become a miracle.
生まれた
The feelings...
思いが
...that were born...
明日へと 導くよ
...will lead us to tomorrow.
私だけの光 放ちたい
I want to emit my own unique light.
DIVE!
WOW WOW WOW WOW
JAPANの美術史♪
JAPAN's Art History♪
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW!
Let's learn it all!
さあ、3Dライブの途中ではございますが、ここで日本美術史の授業を始めたいと思います！
Now, even though we are in the middle of our 3D live stream, I would like to begin our Japanese art history lesson!
は〜い皆さんこんにちは！美術史を学ぶ時間です！
Hello everyone! It's time to learn about art history!
まずは縄文 弥生 古墳まで やってみよう！
First, let's explore from Jomon, Yayoi, to Kofun!
火焔型土器、遮光器土偶、縄文のビーナス！
Flame-like vessels, Shako-ki dogu, and the Venus of Jomon!
銅鐸、銅戈、銅矛、銅剣、弥生土器！
Dotaku, Doka, Doho, Doken, and Yayoi pottery!
埴輪も色々、踊る人々、挂甲武人、馬型埴輪！
Various haniwa, dancing people, armored warriors, and horse haniwa!
古墳出土の鉄刀、鉄剣、七支刀に土師器 須恵器！
Iron sabers and swords from Kofun, Seven-Branched Sword, Haji and Sue pottery!
OK OK OK OK、いい感じ！
OK, OK, OK, OK, looking good!
次は飛鳥に奈良時代！ 3、2、1、ゴー！
Next up is the Asuka and Nara periods! 3, 2, 1, go!
仏像いっぱい釈迦如来、菩薩と合わせて三尊像！
Plentiful Buddhist statues like Shaka Nyorai, forming Triads with Bodhisattvas!
玉虫厨子、天寿国繍帳、金堂壁画、古墳壁画！
Tamamushi Shrine, Tenjukoku Shucho tapestry, Kondo murals, and Kofun murals!
東大寺には奈良の大仏、興福寺には阿修羅像！
Great Buddha of Nara at Todai-ji, Ashura statue at Kofuku-ji!
音と一緒に遊びましょう！
Let's play along with the beat!
螺鈿紫檀五絃琵琶！
Raden Shitan Gogen Biwa!
未来のキミに届くように
So it reaches the future you,
繋いでいこう この想い
let's pass down this passion.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there is love, we'll be fine,
語り合う朝が来るまで
until the morning we talk about it arrives.
JAPANの美術史♪
JAPAN's Art History♪
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW!
Let's learn it all!
まだまだ色々ございます。がんばってついてきてくださいね！
There's still plenty more to go. Please do your best to keep up!
平安 鎌倉 南北朝、参る！
Heian, Kamakura, and Nanboku-cho... Here we go!
曼荼羅、一木造り、寄木造り！
Mandala, ichiboku-zukuri, and yosegi-zukuri!
鳥獣人物戯画に源氏物語！
Chogu Jinbutsu Giga scroll and The Tale of Genji!
平等院鳳凰堂阿弥陀如来坐像！
The Seated Amida Nyorai of Byodoin Ho-o-do!
模様がとってもかわいい
Its patterns are so cute,
片輪車螺鈿手箱！
the Katawuraguruma Raden Tebako!
東大寺の南大門の金剛力士像！
The Kongo Rikishi statues at Todai-ji's Nandaimon Gate!
阿弥陀二十五菩薩来迎図、山越阿弥陀図
Descent of Amida and 25 Bodhisattvas, Amida Rising over Hills,
蒙古襲来絵詞、空也上人像！
Scroll of the Mongol Invasions, and the statue of Kuya Shonin!
一遍上人絵伝、後三年合戦絵巻！
Illustrated Biography of Priest Ippen, and Gosannen War Scroll!
YOYO! 半分くらい来たぜ多分！
YOYO! We're probably about halfway through!
まだまだいくぜ、ありのまま！
Keep it going, just as we are!
室町から安土桃山！
From Muromachi to Azuchi-Momoyama!
能面 翁に枯山水！
Noh mask of Okina, and dry landscape gardens!
天橋立図、呂洞賓図！
View of Ama-no-Hashidate, and Lu Dongbin painting!
狩野派の屏風！
Folding screens of the Kano School!
曜変天目茶碗！
Yohen Tenmoku tea bowl!
洛中洛外図屏風！
Rakuchu Rakugai-zu folding screen!
唐獅子図屏風、松鷹図！
Chinese Lions screen, and Pine and Hawk painting!
職人尽図、花下遊楽図！
Scenes of Various Craftsmen, and Amusements Under Blossom!
松林図、山水図、八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱！
Pine Trees screen, Landscapes, and Yatsuhashi Inkstone Box!
ほんものおおお！！！
IT'S THE REAL ONE!!!
未来のキミに届くように
So it reaches the future you,
繋いでいこう この想い
let's pass down this passion.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there is love, we'll be fine,
語り合う朝が来るまで
until the morning we talk about it arrives.
ここまでついてきてくれてありがとう！なんと今回特別に、バーチャル八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱さんに来ていただきました！ありがとうございます！
Thank you for keeping up so far! Unbelievably, we have a very special guest today: the Virtual Yatsuhashi Inkstone Box! Thank you so much!
あとちょっと、最後までがんばろう！
Just a bit more left, let's do our best until the end!
さあ最後、江戸時代から昭和まで！いきますよ！ 3、2、1、ゴー！
Now, the final stretch, from Edo to Showa period! Here we go! 3, 2, 1, go!
舟橋蒔絵硯箱、風神雷神図屏風
Funabashi Inkstone Box, Wind God and Thunder God screen,
燕子花図屏風、見返り美人！
Irises screen, and Beauty Looking Back!
好色一代男、奥の細道！
The Life of an Amorous Man, and The Narrow Road to the Deep North!
奥の細道
The Narrow Road to the Deep North
富嶽三十六景
Thirty-Six Views of Mount Fuji
東海道中膝栗毛
Tokaidouchu Hizakurige
老猿、ゆあみ、坑夫
Old Monkey, Bathing, Coal Miner
墓守、伎芸天
Grave Keeper, Gigeiten
竜虎図、黒き猫
Dragon and Tiger, Black Cat
鮭、海の幸
Salmon, Bounty of the Sea
渡頭の夕暮
Dusk at the Ferry
麗子微笑、紫禁城
Reiko's Smile, Forbidden City
斑猫、五浦釣人
Tabby Cat, Izura Fisherman
太陽の塔
Tower of the Sun
吉原治良の円
Yoshihara Jiro's Circle
東山魁夷の道
Higashiyama Kaii's Road
未来のキミに届くように
So that it reaches you in the future
繋いでいこう この想い
Let's pass along these feelings
愛さえあれば大丈夫
As long as there is love, it will be alright
語り合おう 朝が来るまで
Let's talk together until morning comes
未来まで
Until the future
最後いくぞ！
Here we go, the last part!
JAPANの美術史♪
JAPAN's Art History♪
お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！ありがとう！
O-Bo-E-Ma-SHOW! Thank you!
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、こんばんは！
Good evening, everyone who is watching the live stream!
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで、らでの小話美術解説のお時間です！
Although we are in the middle of the live performance, now it is time for Raden's Art Commentary!
なんと、今回ご紹介するのは、こちらでございます！ジャジャン！
And what I am going to introduce today is this! Ta-dah!
国宝「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」ということで、
The National Treasure, "Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Suzuribako" (Writing Box with Eight Bridges and Iris Design in Maki-e and Mother-of-Pearl)!
今回、特別に東京国立博物館さんから3Dモデルをお借りしました！
This time, we specially borrowed the 3D model from the Tokyo National Museum!
うふふ、皆様にもよく見てもらいましょう。こちらでございます！
Hehehe, let me show you all in detail. Here it is!
こちらが、バーチャル「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」です！
This is the virtual "Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Suzuribako"!
螺鈿って、なんか、どっかで聞いたことがありますね、なんか。
Raden... I feel like I've heard that word somewhere before.
そんな名前のバーチャルYouTuberがいるような、いないような。
Like there is a virtual YouTuber with that name, or maybe not.
こちらは、私のオリジナル曲「JAPANの美術史♪ お・ぼ・え・ま・SHOW！」にも登場する作品です！
This is a work that also appears in my original song "JAPAN's Art History♪ O-Bo-E-Ma-SHOW!"!
どうですか皆様、この輝きとデザイン！
How do you like this brilliance and design, everyone?
大胆かつ、花びらの装飾の細かい部分も美しいこちらの作品、
This work is both bold and beautiful in its detailed petal decorations.
作ったのは、尾形光琳という人です。
It was made by a person named Ogata Korin.
彼がこの硯箱を作ったのは江戸時代なんですが、
He made this writing box during the Edo period,
どこかモダンな要素も感じることができます。
but you can also feel some modern elements in it.
さて、工芸品を見る時、様々な見方がありますが、
Now, when looking at crafts, there are various ways to view them,
手助けになるのは、作品名です。では、スライド行きます。
but what helps is the name of the work. Now, let's move to the slide.
えー、この工芸品の名前を復習しましょう。八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱。
Let's review the name of this craft: Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Suzuribako.
漢字がたくさん入っていますが、一つ一つ紐解いていきます。
It contains a lot of kanji, but we will break them down one by one.
まずは「八橋」
First, "Yatsuhashi" (Eight Bridges).
日本美術史における工芸品は、物語の一場面や、和歌、歌ですね、がテーマになっていることが少なくありません。
In Japanese art history, crafts are often themed around scenes from stories or waka (poems).
そして、この硯箱もその一つ。
And this writing box is one of them.
「伊勢物語」第九段「三河国八ツ橋」の場面が主題になっているんですよ。なので、これは橋ですね。
It is based on the scene of "Yatsuhashi in Mikawa Province" from Section 9 of "The Tales of Ise." So, this represents the bridges.
八橋。この場面に出てくる8つの橋のこと。
Yatsuhashi. The eight bridges that appear in this scene.
つまりは、何を描いたかを表しています。
In other words, it represents what was depicted.
では、何を描いたかが分かったら、次に、
Now that we know what was depicted, next is...
どんな技法が使われたか。それを表すのが「蒔絵」そして「螺鈿」です。
what techniques were used. That is represented by "Maki-e" and "Raden".
蒔絵とは、簡単に言うと、金粉を漆という接着剤を用いて貼り付けたもの。
Simply put, maki-e is gold powder applied using lacquer as an adhesive.
ここで言うと、カキツバタの葉っぱの部分ですね。ぴんぴんってなっている部分です。
In this case, it's the leaves of the Japanese irises. The spiky parts.
次に「螺鈿」とは、貝殻の光沢のある部分を薄くして貼り付けたもの。
Next, "Raden" is thinly sliced, lustrous parts of shells applied to the surface.
ここで言うと、カキツバタのお花の部です。
In this case, it's the flowers of the irises.
この作品に使われているのはアワビ貝で、花びらを表現するために、あえて穴の空いた貝を使用しているのが分かります。
Abalone shells are used in this work, and you can see that she purposely used shells with holes to depict the petals.
そして最後に、そもそもこれは何か。それを表すのが「硯箱」です。
And finally, what actually is this object? That is represented by "Suzuribako" (writing box).
えー、真ん中をご覧ください。こちら。
Please look at the middle. This part.
えー、墨汁を作る「硯入れ」が上の段にあり、
The upper tray contains the inkstone used to make ink,
さらに、その段の下。えー、下の段は、料紙、紙入れになっています。
and below that tray... The lower tray is for ryoshi, writing paper.
さあ、これで「八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱」の言葉の紐解きが完了しましたね。
Now, we have finished breaking down the words of "Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Suzuribako"!
カキツバタが咲く、川に架かる橋のダイナミックな魅力にも大注目のこの硯箱、
In this writing box, please also pay close attention to the dynamic charm of the bridges over the river where the irises bloom.
パカッと開けると、波が描かれています。
When you open it, waves are painted inside.
もう、ここまで聞いたら、なぜそこに波の意匠を施したのか、皆様ならお分かりですね？
Now that you've heard this much, you probably understand why the wave design was applied there, right?
上の段にある「橋」の、下の...
Below the "bridges" on the upper tray...
「波」ということですね。
Waves, indeed.
実はですね、こちらの八橋蒔絵螺鈿硯箱、
Actually, this Yatsuhashi Maki-e Raden Inkstone Box...
普段展示される際は、箱を閉じた状態なんですよ。
...is usually exhibited with its lid closed.
つまり、中の様子をご覧いただけるのは、
So, being able to see the inside...
この配信ならではの貴重な機会です！
...is a rare opportunity unique to this stream!
こちらがなんと！
And surprisingly,
2026年5月26日から8月16日、本館2室にて展示されるとのことで、
from May 26th to August 16th, 2026, it will be exhibited in Room 2 of the Main Building!
東京国立博物館さんで、ぜひ見てみていただければと思います！
Please go and see it for yourself at the Tokyo National Museum!
このね、波のね、細かいところがすごく…
These fine details of the waves are just...
これ、筆でやってるんですからね。筆でこうやって…
They painted this with a brush. With a brush, like...
あ、お時間となってしまいました。
Ah, it looks like our time is up.
それでは皆さん、また次回お会いしましょう！
Well then, everyone, see you next time!
特報
Special Announcement
特報 その①
Special Announcement Part 1
儒烏風亭らでん ×
Juufutei Raden x
東京国立博物館
Tokyo National Museum
未来の君に届くように
May it reach the future you...
繋いでいこう この想い
...as we pass on these feelings.
愛さえあれば大丈夫
With love, everything will be alright.
語り合おう 朝が来るまで
Let's keep talking until morning comes.
ということで、なんと！
So, surprisingly...
私、儒烏風亭らでんと…
I, Juufutei Raden, and...
東京国立博物館さんとのコラボが決定しましたー！
the Tokyo National Museum will be collaborating!
すごい！
Amazing!
みんな、やったよー！
Everyone, we did it!
もうね、らでん配信とか、もう色んなところで
I've been saying on my streams and in various other places...
東博さんがね、ずっと大好きだって言ってたんですけれども、
...how much I love Tohaku,
今回ね、念願の東博らでんコラボでございます！すごい！
and now, my dream Tohaku-Raden collaboration is finally happening! Amazing!
あら？「東博」、さっき名前聞きましたね？そうです。
Oh? 'Tohaku'? You heard that name just a moment ago, right? That's right!
先日ね、10月から京都、1月から東京にて開催予定の
特別展「源氏物語 王朝のかがやき」展の
Special Exhibition: 'The Tale of Genji: Radiant Culture of the Japanese Imperial Court',
音声ガイドのスペシャルトラックを
I was announced to be in charge of the special track...
務めさせていただくことが発表されましたが、
for the audio guide...
これね、これチラシね、
This is the flyer, by the way!
なんと、この特別展「源氏物語」展の
And surprisingly, the Tokyo venue for this special 'Tale of Genji' exhibition...
東京会場となる東京国立博物館さんとも…
...which is the Tokyo National Museum...
あ、ごめんなさい（笑）
Ah, sorry! (laughs)
東京国立博物館様との…
With the Tokyo National Museum...
コラボが決定いたしましたー！すごい！
our collaboration is officially decided! Awesome!
開催時期は、この「源氏物語」展と同じ、
It is scheduled to run at the same time as 'The Tale of Genji' exhibition...
2027年1月に実施予定となっております！
in January 2027!
なので、こっちは「源氏物語展 儒烏風亭らでんコラボ」、
So we have 'The Tale of Genji Exhibition x Juufutei Raden Collaboration',
そして同じ1月に、東京国立博物館 儒烏風亭らでんコラボがあると。
and also in January, the 'Tokyo National Museum x Juufutei Raden Collaboration'!
もっと簡単に言うと、来年の1月は、
To put it more simply, next January...
東博の色んなところにらでんちゃんがね、
Raden-chan will be appearing...
出現しちゃいます！っていう感じです！
...all over Tohaku! That's how it is!
こちら詳細はですね、また続報をお待ちいただければと思います！
For more details, please look forward to future announcements!
すごいでしょー！すごい、すごい！
Isn't that amazing? It's so amazing!
ということで、本日の重大発表1つ目は、
So, the first major announcement for today...
東博・儒烏風亭らでんコラボでございました！
...was the Tohaku x Juufutei Raden collaboration!
みんなありがとうー！
Thank you everyone!
さあ、ライブも重大発表もまだまだ続きます。
Now, both the live performance and major announcements will continue.
ちょっと待って、ちょっと疲れちゃった（笑）
Hold on. I'm a bit tired. (laughs)
ってことでね、あの、東博…
So, you know, Tohaku...
元々らでんが日本美術史に興味持ったのって、
The reason I first got interested in Japanese art history...
東博さんので、能面を見て、
...was because I saw a Noh mask at Tohaku.
その時に「わぁ、なんて美しいんだ！」って思ったし、
At that time, I thought, 'Wow, how beautiful!'
「らでんって日本で生まれ育ったのに、日本のこと本当に何も知らないんだな」って思ったのがきっかけで、
and realized, 'I was born and raised in Japan, but I know nothing about it.' That was the trigger.
そこから、なんやかんやあって、
From there, through various events...
日本美術史勉強したりして、
I studied Japanese art history...
なんやかんやあって、ホロライブに入って、
...and through more events, I joined Hololive...
なんやかんやあって、今こんな素敵なお衣装をお披露目して、
...and then I got to reveal this wonderful outfit today...
なんやかんやあって、こんなありがたいコラボを
and now, thanks to all those twists and turns,
させていただくことになりました！
I'm able to do this amazing collaboration!
みんなのおかげだよ！ありがとうー！
It's all thanks to everyone! Thank you!
もう人生本当に何が起こるか分かりません。
You really never know what will happen in life.
もうとんでもない。何がどう、
It's unbelievable. How things...
未来へと繋がっていくのか、みたいなことも、
will connect to the future...
もう分かりません。人生は奇妙な冒険みたいなもんでございますな。
...is completely unpredictable. Life really is like a bizarre adventure.
さあ、ということでそろそろ次の曲に行きたいと思います。
All right, so with that, I'd like to move on to the next song.
それでは聴いてください。
Please listen...
「ココロパズルリズム」
...'Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm'.
はぁーーー
Ah~~~
はぁー
Ah...
ココロンパズル
The heart's puzzle
ココロンリズム
The heart's rhythm
ココロンパズル
The heart's puzzle
ココロンリズム
The heart's rhythm
これからの未来 ほらたくさんのピース
Our future ahead, look, so many pieces
組み立てるのはキミしだい
It's up to you to assemble them
一つずつの明日を生きる
Living each tomorrow step by step
ココロンパズルとリズム
The heart's puzzle and rhythm
うまくは言えないけど
I can't put it well into words, but
不思議と安心して
strangely, I feel at ease
いられる感覚って
being able to feel this way...
まるでパズルみたいだ
...it's just like a puzzle
もうずっと前から
For a very long time now,
僕らは予約席
we've held reserved seats
さあ両手つないで
Come, let's hold hands
きっと一つになれる
We can surely become one
完成が見えていても
Even if the completion is in sight,
すんなりとはいかないね
it doesn't go smoothly, does it?
それぞれが夢のカケラだね
Each of them is a piece of a dream
これからの未来 ほらたくさんのピース
Our future ahead, look, so many pieces
組み立てるのはキミしだい
It's up to you to assemble them
一つずつの明日を生きる
Living each tomorrow step by step
空いた隙間を埋める
Filling in the empty gaps
楽しいこともきっとあるけど
I'm sure there will be fun times, too,
それよりも大切なのは
but what's more important than that...
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
...is that when we are sad or happy,
一緒に泣ける そんなココロンパズル
we can cry together; that's our heart's puzzle
すんなりとはいかないね
It doesn't go smoothly, does it?
キミと僕のパズルの行方も
Even the fate of our puzzle...
これからのlove story ほらたくさんのピース
Our love story from here on, look, so many pieces
間違えることもあるけど 胸に刻み
We might make mistakes, but etching them in our hearts,
明日を生きる
we live for tomorrow
空いた隙間を埋める
Filling in the empty gaps
楽しいこともきっとあるけど
I'm sure there will be fun times, too,
それよりも大切なのは
but what's more important than that...
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
...is that when we are sad or happy,
一緒に泣ける そんなココロンリズム
we can cry together; that's our heart's rhythm
don't cry don't cry
walk hand in hand
ah ah
繋いで
Holding hands
it's a nice day
これからの未来 ほらたくさんのピース
Our future ahead, look, so many pieces
組み立てるのはキミしだい
It's up to you to assemble them
一つずつの明日を生きる
Living each tomorrow step by step
空いた隙間を埋める
Filling in the empty gaps
楽しいこともきっとあるけど
I'm sure there will be fun times, too,
それよりも大切なのは
but what's more important than that...
悲しかったり 嬉しいときに
...is that when we are sad or happy,
一緒に泣ける そんなココロンパズル
we can cry together; that's our heart's puzzle
そんなココロンリズム
that's our heart's rhythm
はぁー
Ah...
ライブをご覧になってる皆さま、こんばんは！
Good evening to everyone watching the live stream!
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで、らでの小話美術解説の時間でーす！
We are in the middle of the live show, but now it's time for Raden's Quick Art Lecture!
今回ご紹介するのは...
What I will be introducing this time is...
こちらでん！ジャジャーン！
...this! Ta-dah!
クロード・モネ『睡蓮の池』
Claude Monet's "The Water-Lily Pond"
今回なんと ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしております！
For this, we've actually borrowed the image from the National Gallery in London!
本当にありがとうございます！
Thank you very much indeed!
皆さんどうですか？
What do you think, everyone?
私 モネの描く世界が大好きなんです
I absolutely love the world Monet paints.
まあ モネといえば日本でもとても人気の高い画家ですが
Monet is a very popular painter in Japan,
彼の絵画の魅力はどのようなところにあるのでしょうか？
but where does the charm of his paintings lie?
今回は 彼の絵画に内在する魅力を言語化していきましょう
This time, let's put the charm inherent in his paintings into words.
この作品は1899年頃描かれました
This work was painted around 1899.
緑色の光が溢れる睡蓮の池には
In the water-lily pond overflowing with green light,
大きな橋が架かり 橋の奥には柳が描かれています
a large bridge is built, and willows are painted behind it.
実はこの場所 モネの自宅に作った池なんです
Actually, this pond was built right at Monet's home.
フランスのジヴェルニーという街に家を購入した彼は
Having purchased a house in Giverny, France,
近隣の川から水を引いて 自分の理想とする庭を作りました
he drew water from a nearby river to create his ideal garden.
アーチ状の大きな橋 これ いわゆる太鼓橋と呼ばれる橋と 柳
A large arched bridge—a so-called drum bridge—and willows.
あれ？なんだか日本っぽさを感じませんか？
Wait, don't you feel a kind of Japanese influence?
それもそのはず 彼は日本の浮世絵に強く影響を受けた画家でした
No wonder, as he was highly influenced by Japanese ukiyo-e.
彼の描く絵は光に溢れていて
His paintings are overflowing with light,
目の前で風が吹いて水面が揺れているようにも見えます
looking as if the wind is blowing and the water is rippling before you.
じーっと見ていると 水も 花も 木も 橋も 空気でさえも溶けていくようです
Staring at it, the water, flowers, trees, bridge, and even air seem to melt.
見ていて落ち着く絵画だと思いませんか？
Don't you think it's a painting that brings tranquility?
モネは絵を描くとき 色を混ぜて塗るのではなく
When Monet painted, instead of mixing colors together,
純粋な 何も混ざっていない色を 置くように塗りました
he applied pure, unmixed colors side by side.
色は 混ぜれば混ぜるほど 塗り重ねれば重ねるほど 暗くなっていきます
The more you mix colors or layer them, the darker they get.
彼はこの課題を「色を置く」ことによって解決し 光に溢れた絵画の表現に成功したんです
He solved this by "placing colors," succeeding in creating a light-filled painting.
この絵画に近づいてみると 筆跡がしっかり残っています
If you look closely, the brushstrokes are clearly left behind.
隣り合った絵の具 一つ一つの相乗効果を計算し
He calculated the synergistic effect of each adjacent paint,
絵の具の塊から 温度感や湿度感を感じることができる風景へと変貌する表現は モネが生涯かけて研究していたものです
turning lumps of paint into a landscape of temperature and humidity—a lifelong research.
光を求めたモネが 陰影のない日本の浮世絵に強く惹かれたのも理解できますね
It's easy to see why Monet, seeking light, was drawn to shadowless ukiyo-e.
彼の絵画の明るさは 画家としての研究の成果であり 情熱さえ感じられる そんな作品だと私は感じます
I feel the brightness of his work is a result of research, filled with passion.
みんなはこの絵画 どう読んだかな？
How did you all interpret this painting?
実はモネは印象派の画家と呼ばれるきっかけを作った人でもあるんですが
Actually, Monet was also the one who triggered the Impressionist movement,
それはまた別のお話
but that's another story.
という感じでございまして こちらはロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんにて見ることができます！
And there you have it, you can view this at the National Gallery in London!
ぜひ行ってみてください！
Please go and visit!
また次回！
See you next time!
I want to fight your brother
Let's KUNG FU!
Every night I look to the skies and wonder what we did
Always a naive point of view that breaks us in the end
If I could find the meaning of it all I'd take the chance
Maybe in time we'll walk the mile and change it if we can
It's now and always
How did we get this far, did we get this far now
ALWAYS
We're making a brand new start, just a brand new start now
Nothing will hold me down, never hold me down now
ALWAYS
Wave goodbye to me!
Around the world 新しいことに
Around the world, to new things...
Around the world フミダスチカラで
Around the world, with the strength to step forward...
Around the world 世界は変わるさ
Around the world, the world will change.
But don't run away 'cause if it's not ok!
I'll change that world into something better, honey!
Let's KUNG FU!
果てしなく広がるこの大地を 僕らはまた
Across this endlessly spreading earth, we will once again...
...僕らはまた 歩き続けるさ
...we'll keep on walking again.
すべての意味が分かるのならば
If we knew the meaning of everything...
この瞳で何を見つめるのだろう
What would we gaze at with these eyes?
IT'S NOW AND ALWAYS
(HOW DID WE GET THIS FAR? DID WE GET THIS FAR NA~)
ALWAYS
(WE'RE MAKING A BRAND NEW START, JUST A BRAND NEW START NA~)
(NOTHING WILL HOLD ME DOWN, NEVER HOLD ME DOWN NA~)
ALWAYS
WAVE GOOD BYE TO ME!
Wave goodbye to me!
AROUND THE WORLD 君だけのために
Around the world, just for you
AROUND THE WORLD 探し続けるよ
Around the world, I'll keep searching
AROUND THE WORLD 奇跡のかけらを
Around the world, the fragments of miracles
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK!
But don't run away, 'cause if it's not okay!
YEAH EY AND YOU KNOW IT'S GONNA BE RAINING
AND YOU KNOW IT'S GONNA BE HARD
AS LONG AS WE TRUST EACH OTHER
NOTHING'S GONNA BREAK APART OH NO! NO!
IF YA WANNA BE SOMEBODY, GET UP ON YA FEET AND GO
I KNOW WE'RE GONNA MEET EACH OTHER SOMEWHERE AROUND THE GLOBE
AROUND THE WORLD
AROUND THE WORLD いつでも自分に
Around the world, always to myself
AROUND THE WORLD 負けている人は
Around the world, those who are losing
AROUND THE WORLD 何も掴めない
Around the world, cannot grasp anything
BUT DON'T RUN AWAY CAUSE IF IT'S NOT OK!
But don't run away, 'cause if it's not okay!
I'LL CHANGE THAT WORLD INTO SOMETHING BETTER HONEY!
特報 その②
[Special Announcement Part 2]
儒烏風亭らでん × THE NATIONAL GALLERY LONDON
[Juufuutei Raden × The National Gallery, London]
儒烏風亭らでん ロンドン ナショナル・ギャラリー コラボ決定!!
[Juufuutei Raden & London National Gallery Collaboration Confirmed!!]
ハレとケでテンポにのって あなたに...
Riding the tempo of ordinary and extraordinary days, to you...
この想い 純粋に伝えたい
I want to convey these feelings purely...
あたし世界 見せてあげる
I will show you the world.
絵画一番 やっちゃって
Art is number one, let's do it!
ファンファーレに風吹いて 打ち立てる
The wind blows through the fanfare, establishing...
キャンバスと交わり 時を越え
interacting with the canvas, crossing time.
手拍子に乗せて
Riding on the handclaps...
いってらっしゃい 見てらっしゃい
Off you go, come and see!
はぁ〜、はい！
Phew, okay!
ということで、なんと！
So, guess what!
私、儒烏風亭らでんと
I, Juufuutei Raden, and...
ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボが決定しましたー！
my collaboration with the London National Gallery has been confirmed!
ナショナル・ギャラリーさんといえば
Speaking of the National Gallery,
モネ、ゴッホ、ターナー...
Monet, Van Gogh, Turner...
もう、とにかく色んな画家さんたちの超有名な作品をいっぱい所蔵されているところなんですが
it's a place that houses so many famous works by various painters!
なんと、そんなナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ
And guess what, this collaboration with the National Gallery is called...
「儒烏風亭らでんの瞳に映る 世界の名画」
"The World's Masterpieces Reflected in Juufuutei Raden's Eyes"
〜A SHARED ART JOURNEY〜 コラボ決定です！すごい！
"~A Shared Art Journey~"! The collaboration is confirmed! Amazing!
さあ、これで、とある3つの名画とコラボしてるんですが、みんなわかるかな？
Now, we are collaborating with three specific masterpieces. Can everyone guess what they are?
3つね、3つあるんだけど
Three of them, there are three.
えー、では、左からいきましょうか。
Well, shall we start from the left?
えー、左、ターナー 「雨、蒸気、速度―グレート・ウェスタン鉄道」
On the left is Turner's "Rain, Steam, and Speed - The Great Western Railway".
そして、真ん中、モネの 「睡蓮の池」
And in the middle is Monet's "The Water-Lily Pond".
オフィス、一番右、これは皆さんお分かりでしょう、ゴッホの「ひまわり」
And on the far right, you all probably know this, is Van Gogh's "Sunflowers"!
そして今回、コラボ商品が
And this time, we have collaboration merchandise!
ございます！全8種あるんですよ。じゃあ、1つずつね、ちょっと紹介していきましょうか。だんっ！
There are eight types in total! Let's introduce them one by one. Ta-dah!
はい！
Yes!
えー、まず左上からいきましょうか。
Let's start from the top left.
まずはフレグランスミストセットです。
First is the Fragrance Mist Set.
らでんが監修・考案したフレグランスミスト。3点の名画が持つイメージを香りで表現しました。
This fragrance mist was supervised and designed by Raden. We expressed the images of the three masterpieces through scents.
本商品はアルコールフリーのフレグランスミストなので、色んな場面に合わせて使用可能です。
Since this product is an alcohol-free fragrance mist, you can use it to suit various occasions.
じゃあ、お隣いきましょうか。
Next, let's move to the one beside it.
えー、その隣、ローラーボールペン。3つの名画のエッセンスと儒烏風亭らでんの家紋を見事に融合させたデザインでございます。
Beside it is the Rollerball Pen. It features a design that beautifully fuses the essence of the three masterpieces with Juufuutei Raden's family crest.
えー、じゃあ次は
And next...
左下、えー、カップ&ソーサーセット。
On the bottom left, the Cup & Saucer Set.
描き下ろしイラストからインスピレーションを得た、ボーンチャイナ製のカップ&ソーサーセットでございます。
This bone china cup and saucer set is inspired by the newly drawn illustration.
ソーサーの中心には儒烏風亭らでんの名前も記載されています。
Juufuutei Raden's name is also printed at the center of the saucer.
最近らでんも紅茶飲めるようになったんでお揃いにしましょうや！
Lately, I've also become able to drink black tea, so let's match!
えー、そしてその隣がスカーフ！
And next to that is the Scarf!
新たに描き下ろしたイラスト要素を組み合わせ...
combining the newly drawn illustration elements...
ファッション性と実用性を兼ね備えたデザインスカーフでございます。
It's a design scarf that combines fashionability and practicality.
え、そして、じゃ、その隣行こか。えー、アクリルスタンド！本コラボならではの新衣装に身にまとうアクリルスタンドでございます。
Next, let's look at the neighboring item. Acrylic stands! Featuring the new costumes unique to this collaboration.
えー、じゃあ、右上行きましょう。キャンバスアート！描き下ろしイラストを使用されるキャンバスアートでございます。
Next, let's look at the top right. Canvas art! Canvas art using newly drawn illustrations.
その下はトートバッグ。表面には本コラボのために描き下ろされたイラスト、裏面には3点の絵画のディテールをあしらったデザインの両面仕様となっています。
Below that is the tote bag. The front features an illustration drawn for this collab, and the back is a double-sided design with details from three paintings.
そして最後、ランダムクリアカードになります。全6種のランダムクリアカードで、一部のカードには箔押しデジタルサインと特別メッセージが入っていますよ！
And finally, the random clear cards. Out of 6 random designs, some cards feature a gold-foiled digital signature and a special message!
グッズ、いいでしょう？どれも素敵でしょう？そして、さらに...
The merch is great, right? They're all so wonderful. And what's more...
グッズだけではございません。ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボで、音声ガイドも収録させていただきました！
Merch is not all we have. Through this collab with the National Gallery, London, we've also recorded an audio guide!
すごーい！
Amazing!
しかも、こちらね、なんとロンドンの公式チャンネルにてアップする予定でございますが、
And what's more, it is planned to be uploaded to the official channel of London,
詳細は後日公開予定となりますので、続報をお待ちください！
but the details will be released at a later date, so please look forward to further updates!
と、グッズとガイドと盛りだくさんなんですが、みんな、ロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリー、どんなとこか... あ、ごめんなさい。
So, there's lots of merch and the guide, but does everyone know what kind of place the National Gallery, London is... Ah, sorry.
ちょっと待ってな。ロンドンの...
Hold on a second. The...
ナショナル・ギャラリー、どんなところか気になりませんか？
Aren't you curious about what kind of place the National Gallery is?
ロンドンの街並み、見てみたくないですか？
Don't you want to see the streets of London?
ということで、なんと、実は、ReGLOSSメンバーで、ロンドンロケに行ってきました！わー！
So actually, the ReGLOSS members went on a location shoot in London! Yay!
そのロケの様子はReGLOSSチャンネルなどで後日公開予定となっておりますので、こちらもぜひお楽しみに！
The footage of the shoot is scheduled to be released on the ReGLOSS channel and elsewhere later, so look forward to this too!
ということで、重大告知その2は、儒烏風亭らでんとロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボでございました！ありがとう！
So, major announcement number two was the collaboration between Juufuutei Raden and the National Gallery, London! Thank you!
そして、今、スタッフさんの方から、どうやら今、Xで、これXですか？Xでトレンド2位だそうです！すごーい！みんなありがとう！
Also, from the staff, it seems that we are currently trending at number 2 on X! Is this X? Trending 2nd! Amazing! Thank you everyone!
大丈夫かな？トレンド2位に入った理由が「らでんちゃんの体力が心配です」でめっちゃ入ってたらどうしようかな？
Is it okay? What if the reason we trended at number 2 was because of tweets like "I'm worried about Raden-chan's stamina"?
でも、今日は、今日はもう、体力がもう、すっからかんになって、次の日動けなくなるまで頑張るって、らでんは決めたんです。
But today, Raden decided to work hard until my stamina is completely empty and I can't move the next day.
だから、今日はみんなもね、いっぱい、いっぱい楽しんでほしいです。どうですか？皆さん、ついてこられてますか？
So today, I want everyone to have lots and lots of fun. How is it? Is everyone keeping up?
あ、待ってくださいね。重大発表、まだあるんです！まだあるんです！これで終わりじゃないんですよ！
Oh, wait a second. There are still major announcements! There's more! This isn't the end!
しかも、ライブもまだまだ続きますので、皆さんチャンネルはそのままで。ですよ。
And the live performance will still continue, so stay tuned to the channel!
では、次の曲に行きたいと思います。
Now, let's move on to the next song.
それでは、どうぞ！
Here it is!
水面に映った藍
Indigo, reflected on the surface of the water,
眩しく揺れる
sways dazzlingly.
手探りで探してた
I searched by touch...
足りない私
...for the missing parts of me.
ゆっくりと動き出した
Everything slowly began to move,
何万年も前から
from tens of thousands of years ago,
この時を約束されていた
as if this moment had been promised,
みたいに ほら
just like that, look.
風は歌い
The wind sings,
透明な空から
From the clear sky
真っ直ぐに
Straight
差し込んだ
pierced
優しい朝日
a gentle morning sun
過ぎた季節が歪に
The seasons that passed, distorted
削った今という瞬き
and carved away this instant called "now"
どこにも同じものはないの
There's nothing else like it anywhere
ほら
See,
生きてる証
it's proof of being alive
風は歌い
The wind sings
雨は語り
the rain speaks
たどり着くよ
I'll reach it
光のすみかへ
the dwelling of light
幾重にも
Layer upon layer
重なってる
are overlapping
この地球の偶然
the coincidences of this planet
影の向こう
Beyond the shadow
真実の色
the true colors
見つけ出すよ
I will find
光のすみかを
the dwelling of light
一つでも
If even one thing
欠けていたら
had been missing
きっと
we surely
出会えてなかったね
would never have met
ライブをご覧になっている皆様、
To everyone watching the live performance,
こんばんは！
Good evening!
ライブの途中ではございますが、ここで！
We're currently in the middle of the live show, but right here...
らでの小咄 美術解説のお時間です！
It's time for Raden's short art commentary!
今回ご紹介するのは、こちらでーす！じゃーん！
The piece we are introducing this time is this one! Ta-da!
フィンセント・ファン・ゴッホ「ひまわり」
Vincent van Gogh's "Sunflowers"
今回ナショナル・ギャラリーさんより画像をお借りしております
We have borrowed the image from the National Gallery for this
ありがとうございます！
Thank you very much!
ゴッホといえば「ひまわり」というイメージを持っている方も
Many of you might associate Van Gogh with "Sunflowers"
少なくないのではないでしょうか？
I'm sure there are quite a few.
それもそのはず。実はゴッホの描いたひまわりは
And with good reason. Actually, the sunflowers painted by Van Gogh...
一つだけじゃないんです
...is not just a single painting.
この世界に失われたものも含めて
In this world, including those that have been lost,
7つのひまわりがあったんですよ
there were seven "Sunflowers" paintings.
さて、では実際に作品をじっくり見てみましょう！
Now, let's take a closer, careful look at the artwork!
みんなはどんな感想を持ったかな？
What kind of impressions did you all get?
改めて見てみると、色んなことが見えてきます
Looking at it again, we can see various details.
よく見るとひまわりの花の向きはバラバラで
If you look closely, the directions of the sunflowers are all different,
花びらも不揃いですね
and their petals are also uneven, aren't they?
しかし温かい黄色が画面全体を包み込むことで
However, as the warm yellow envelops the entire canvas,
どこか生命力が溢れているようにも見えませんか？
doesn't it somehow seem to overflow with vitality?
ここからはゴッホと黄色、そして
From here on, let's look at Van Gogh and yellow, and...
ゴッホとひまわりについて紐解いていきましょう
...unravel the connection between Van Gogh and sunflowers.
「太陽は淡い硫黄の輝きを伝達するのだ」という言葉を残しているゴッホは
Van Gogh, who left behind the words "The sun transmits a pale sulfur glow,"
太陽の光を黄色で表現しました
expressed sunlight through the color yellow.
そして黄色はゴッホにとって生命力の象徴でもあります
And yellow was also a symbol of vitality for Van Gogh.
この絵を描いたとき、彼は
When he painted this picture, he was...
フランス南部のアルルという街で
...in Arles, a town in southern France,
心機一転、画家として仲間と頑張っていこうと意気込んでいました
and eager to work hard as an artist alongside his peers with a fresh start.
そんな気持ちを黄色に託したのかもしれません
Perhaps he entrusted those feelings to the color yellow.
一方で、この絵のモチーフになっているひまわりについて見てみましょう
On the other hand, let's look at the sunflowers, the painting's motif.
ひまわりは太陽に向かって咲きます
Sunflowers bloom facing the sun.
太陽は西洋美術史において、神を象徴します
In Western art history, the sun symbolizes God.
それに向かって咲くひまわりは
The sunflowers blooming towards it...
崇拝、従順、忠誠、そして信仰心や愛を象徴します
...symbolize adoration, obedience, loyalty, devotion, and love.
ここで、さらに遠回りして、彼の過去について知っていきましょう
Here, let's take a further detour to learn about his past.
先ほどゴッホがアルルでの生活を始めた時、私は
Earlier, when I spoke of Van Gogh starting his life in Arles,
「心機一転」という表現をしました
I used the expression "a fresh start."
実は彼、元々は牧師さんになりたかったんです
Actually, he originally wanted to become a pastor.
彼は頑張って勉強や奉仕活動に注力しますが
He studied hard and focused on missionary work,
上手くいきませんでした
but things didn't go well.
画家への転身は、牧師さんへの道を断たれた後のことだったんですね
His turn to becoming a painter happened after his path to the priesthood was cut off.
そんな彼が描く、信仰の象徴である「ひまわり」
With that background, his painting of "Sunflowers," a symbol of faith,
皆様はどう読み解きますか？
how do you interpret it?
未来への希望 of 光？それとも自分への失望？
A light of hope for the future? Or disappointment in himself?
ゴッホの見た「光のすみか」はひまわりの中にあったのかもしれませんね
The "dwelling of light" Van Gogh saw might have been within sunflowers.
という感じでございまして
And that's the story!
こちらもロンドンのナショナル・ギャラリーさんにて見ることができます！
You can also see this painting at the National Gallery in London!
ぜひぜひ行ってみてください！
Please, please go check it out!
あ、また次回！
Oh, see you next time!
はい、ということで、早いもので次が最後の曲でございますが
And with that, time flies, and the next one is the final song...
なんと、儒烏風亭らでん、新曲をリリースします！
But guess what? Jufutei Raden is releasing a new song!
イェーイ！
Yay!
特報！デジタルリリース！
Breaking news! Digital release!
タイトルは、『Miracle Palette』！
The title is "Miracle Palette"!
はい。えー、こちらですね、楽曲リリースなんですが、5月18日の0時00分
Yes, the digital release of this song is on May 18th at 00:00.
なので、今日のね、日付が変わったタイミングでリリースされます
So, it will be released as soon as the date changes today.
5月18日といえば、そう、皆さん大正解、国際博物館の日でございます！
And speaking of May 18th, yes, you guessed it, it's International Museum Day!
そんなね、特別な日にリリース！
Releasing on such a special day!
そして、この配信が終わってすぐ！
And right after this stream ends!
MVですね。なんとミュージックビデオが公開されます！
The MV, yes! The music video will be released!
儒烏風亭らでん初のダンスてんこ盛り、3D MVとなっております
It is Jufutei Raden's first dance-packed 3D MV!
そしてこちら、楽曲コンセプトはジャズっぽいね、感じになっております
And the concept of this song is a jazz-like feel.
ということで
So...
今から、ライブバージョンの『Miracle Palette』を披露したいと思います！
Right now, I'd like to perform the live version of "Miracle Palette"!
ダンサーの皆さんも！
Dancers, please join me!
わー！よろしくお願いします！お願いします！
Wow! Please look forward to it! Thank you!
はい！ありがとう、キラキラしてくれてありがとう。ありがとうございます
Yes! Thank you, thank you for making it sparkle. Thank you very much!
では、聴いてください。『Miracle Palette』
Now, please listen to "Miracle Palette".
Miracle Palette
暗がりステージに立つ 雨傘を携え
Carry an umbrella and stand on the dim stage
朧に霞む構図 印象 儚く
The composition in the haze, the impression is fleeting
始めましょ 雨粒ドローイング
Let's begin, raindrop drawing
キャンヴァスはこの空、この世界
The canvas is this sky, this world
Hop Hop 飛び回る
hop hop jumping around
Tap Tap 打ち鳴らす
tap tap tapping along
Dance Dance ぐるぐる いざショータイム
dance dance spinning around, time for the show
(Ladies and gentleman, welcome to our magical show!)
スポットライトを浴びて
Bathed in spotlights,
輝きを放つ
shining bright
エンタシスよりプリズム
Prism, from the entasis,
分光をスタンバイ
splitting light, standby
(この鈍色の空に七色の橋を架けて見せましょう)
(Let's build a seven-colored bridge in this dull-colored sky)
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Come on, take a look!
目に映るもの、
What you see
今を彩るから
will color the present
大きな絵筆で 描き出す
In the bold perspective drawn
大胆なパースの中 嗚呼
with a big paintbrush, ah
びしょ濡れの舞台は ミラクルなパレット
The drenched stage is a miracle palette
マスカレイドな第二部の開演
The second part of the masquerade begins,
Shall we dance?
モノトーンから極彩色に
From monotone to vivid colors,
アシンメトリーなグラデーションで
in an asymmetrical gradation
夢中になってほしいの
I want you to be obsessed,
雨雲にマーブリング
marbling the rain clouds
目を奪われたその隙
In the moment you are captivated,
イリュージョンをスタンバイ
standby, illusion
(ところで皆さん、なくし物はございませんか？)
(By the way everyone, are there any lost items?)
どなた様もおいでませ！
Welcome to you all!
あの手この手で魅了していくから
I will fascinate you with every trick
一足お先に まんまと
One step ahead, I'll skillfully
盗みだすわ あなたの心を
steal your heart
光を放ちだすきらめきのパレット
The shining palette that begins to emit light
(さてさて！いよいよ大詰め、クライマックスに向けて盛り上がってまいりましょう！ Listen!)
(Well then! Finally the climax, let's get excited towards the climax! listen!)
OK, 5・4・3・2・1・go on the show!
最大級のキャンヴァスに描き出す
Drawing on the biggest canvas
誰も見たことのない景色
Scenery that no one has ever seen before
さあさ、とくとご覧あれ！
Come on, take a look!
次元の壁を超えて閃くから
Because it glimmers beyond the dimension wall
大きな絵筆で描き出す
Drawing with a big paintbrush
大胆なバースの中
In this daring verse,
さあ みんなで大団円 迎えに行こう
let's all head towards a happy ending together!
嗚呼 びしょ濡れの舞台は ミラクルなパレット
Ah, this soaking wet stage is a miracle palette!
おー
Oh...
特報
[Special News]
その3
[Part 3]
新情報
[New Information]
箱根探訪編
[Hakone Exploration Edition]
儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアム
Juufuutei Raden's Guided Tour: Pixel Museum!
追加ダウンロードコンテンツ 箱根探訪編 配信決定！
Release confirmed for the Hakone Exploration DLC!
イベント展示のご案内
[Information on Event Exhibition]
今回のテーマは... 箱根！
This time's theme is... Hakone!
らでん館長の大好きな 箱根にまつわる作品をご用意！
We have works related to Hakone, which Director Raden loves!
館内もイベント仕様で 箱根の魅力がたっぷり！
The museum is customized for the event, packed with Hakone's charm!
もちろん 解説はフルボイス！
And of course, the commentary is fully voiced!
儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアム
Juufuutei Raden's Guided Tour: Pixel Museum!
追加ダウンロードコンテンツ 箱根探訪編 2026年12月配信予定！
DLC: Hakone Exploration Edition scheduled for December 2026!
ちょっと待つたけねー！
Please wait just a little bit!
な、な、なんと！
W-W-What?!
昨年6月5日の発売から1年を待たずに
Before even a year has passed since its release on June 5th last year...
「儒烏風亭らでんがご案内 ピクセルミュージアム」の
the additional downloadable content for...
追加ダウンロードコンテンツ「箱根探訪編」の配信が決定しました！やったー！
'Juufuutei Raden's Guided Tour: Pixel Museum,' 'Hakone Exploration Edition,' has been confirmed! Yay!
みんながね、いっぱいダウンロードしてくれて、
It's all thanks to everyone downloading it so much,
みんながたくさん遊んでくれたおかげです！本当にありがとうございます！
and playing it a lot! Thank you so very much!
今回の舞台は、皆様お馴染みの「箱根」でございます！
The stage this time is the familiar Hakone!
え、前作に引き続き「箱根ガラスの森美術館」様に加え、
Following the previous game, in addition to the Hakone Glass Forest Museum,
今回はなんと、
this time, incredibly,
「ポーラ美術館」様と「小田急箱根」様にもご協力いただけることとなりました！拍手！
we are also collaborating with the Pola Museum of Art and Odakyu Hakone! Please clap!
え、館長のプライベートルームもイベント仕様にアップデート！
The Director's private room is also updated for the event!
箱根の魅力マシマシでお届けいたしますよ。いいでしょう？
We'll deliver even more Hakone charm. Isn't that great?
そんな追加ダウンロードコンテンツ「箱根探訪編」は、2026年12月に配信予定！
This DLC, Hakone Exploration Edition, is scheduled to be released in December 2026!
さあそしてですね、来週5月23日、24日に
And next week, on May 23rd and 24th,
京都にて開催されます「BitSummit 14th」に「らでピク」も登場！
'Radepiku' will appear at BitSummit 14th held in Kyoto!
大好評発売中の「らでピク」の試遊や、
There will be a demo play of the popular 'Radepiku,'
「箱根探訪編」のキービジュアルポストカードの配布もあるみたいですよ！
and they'll also distribute Hakone Exploration Edition key visual postcards!
詳しい情報は、公式ホームページとジュピターさんの公式Xを要チェックです！
Be sure to check the official homepage and Jupiter's official X account for details!
まだまだ嬉しい情報もあるかも？
There might be even more exciting news!
それでは、リリースまでお楽しみに！
So please look forward to the release!
はい！えーそして、そして、
Yes! And, and...
皆さんお待たせかね、儒烏風亭らでん100万人記念グッズが発売するぞー！
the moment you've all been waiting for, Juufuutei Raden's 1-million subscriber commemorative goods are going on sale!
ごめんね、今日本当に何か発表が多くて。
Sorry, there are really so many announcements today, haha.
え、早速詳細見ていきましょう。1つ目はこちら、デン！
Let's check out the details right away. First is this, ta-da!
新衣装でライブ！アクリルブロック。いや、めっちゃ疲れてる、らでんが映っちゃった。
New Outfit Live! Acrylic Block. Oh, the extremely tired Raden was shown...
新衣装でライブ！アクリルブロック。
New Outfit Live! Acrylic Block.
ライブステージで楽しそうに歌う新衣装のらでん。森倉円先生の描き下ろしでございます。いいでしょう？
Raden singing happily on stage in her new outfit, drawn by Morikura En-sensei. Isn't it wonderful?
こちら、アクリルブロックの表裏に印刷されておりまして、
This is printed on both the front and back of the acrylic block,
めっちゃね、奥行きが感じられるものとなってるんですよ。
making you really feel the depth.
続いてはこちら、デン！
Next is this, ta-da!
はい、らでんの衣装いろいろ3連結アクリルキーホルダー。
Yes, Raden's Various Outfits 3-Link Acrylic Keychain!
新衣装、通常衣装、フラッシュポイント衣装の3種類の3連結アクリルキーホルダーとなっております。
It features her new outfit, default outfit, and Flashpoint outfit connected together.
イラストは、「心パズルリズム」の時の、あの後ろにね、可愛いイラスト流れてたんですけれども、
The illustrations are by the familiar Tsubomilku-sensei, who did the cute illustrations...
でお馴染み、つぼみるく先生でございます！
...shown in the background of 'Kokoro Puzzle Rhythm'!
続いてはこちら、デン！
Next is this, ta-da!
新衣装モチーフピンバッジセット。新衣装をモチーフにしたピンバッジセットですよ。
New Outfit Motif Pin Badge Set. It's a set of pin badges designed after her new outfit!
え、懐中時計、え、それから、今してないけど、マスク、
There are four types: a pocket watch, a mask—which I'm not wearing right now—
シルクハット、モノクルの4種類となっております。
a top hat, and a monocle.
続いてはこちら、デン！
Next is this, ta-da!
ライブ前のトラブル！？ボイス。らでんが書き下ろした台本です。どんなトラブルが...
Trouble Before the Live!? Voice. It's a voice pack scripted by Raden herself. What kind of trouble...
のかは聞いてみてのお楽しみ！
Find out what it sounds like when you listen to it!
そしてフルセット購入特典はこちら、デン！
And here's the bonus for buying the full set! Ta-da!
はい、え、儒烏風亭らでん直筆サイン入り、もりくらえん先生描き下ろしポストカード！
Yes! A postcard illustrated by Morikura En-sensei, hand-signed by Juufuutei Raden.
今回も購入した方全員に、直筆でサインを書かせていただきますよ！
Once again, I'll be hand-signing a card for everyone who buys it.
皆さんに届くように、精一杯書かせていただくので、
I'll put my heart into signing them so they reach you...
よろしくお願いいたします！
So please look forward to it!
さらに、特典ボイスも付きます。こちらも、らでんが書き下ろしてます。
In addition, there's a bonus voice! I wrote the script for this one too.
はい、ということで、もう今日ね、もう、すご、すごい盛りだくさんでございましたが、
Alright, so today, there was so, so much packed in...
皆さん、追いつけてますか？
Are you all keeping up?
結構とんでもない発表をたくさんしたんですけれども、
I made quite a few mind-blowing announcements!
らでんが一番、結構とんでもないなと思っております。
And I think I'm the one who's most blown away by them.
ということで、本日の重大発表は、その1：東京国立博物館さんとのコラボ！
So, today's major announcements are: Number 1, a collaboration with the Tokyo National Museum!
その2：ロンドン・ナショナル・ギャラリーさんとのコラボ！
Number 2, a collaboration with the National Gallery in London!
その3：え、儒烏風亭らでんがご案内、ピクセルミュージアム、ダウンロードコンテンツ発売決定でございます！
And Number 3, the release of the Pixel Museum DLC guided by Juufuutei Raden!
情報量がね、多すぎたと思うので、ぜひアーカイブでも確認してみててください。
Since it was a lot of information, please make sure to check the archive!
そして、このあとは、メン限でアンコールライブあります！
And after this, we have the membership-only Encore Live!
その時にまた、衣装はね、ゆっくりお見せしようかなと思っておりますので、
At that time, I plan to take my time showing you my outfit...
えー、まだの方はチャンネル登録と、えー、気になるよって方はメンバーでね、またアンコールライブでお会いしましょう！
So if you haven't yet, please subscribe, and if you're interested, join the membership and let's meet there!
そして、そして、忘れちゃいけません、このあとすぐ新曲MV公開でございます！
And, and! Lest we forget, the MV for my new song will be released right after this!
頑張って作ったんで、いっぱい見てほしいです！
We worked really hard on it, so I want you all to watch it a lot!
はい！
Yes!
え、ということでございまして、えー、
And so...
日頃応援してくださっている皆々様、見ていただいている、聞いていただいているリスナーの皆様のおかげで、
Thanks to everyone who supports me daily, and to all the listeners watching and listening...
今回ね、このライブを開催することができました。
we were able to hold this 3D Live today.
本当に本当にありがとうございます！とっても嬉しいです！
Thank you so, so much! I am incredibly happy!
これからもね、歌もね、ダンスもね、
From here on, with singing, dancing...
自分のね、やりたいこともいーっぱい頑張っていきますので、ぜひ応援のほどよろしくお願いいたします！
...and doing lots of things I want to do, I'll keep doing my best, so please continue to support me!
それでは！メン限アンコールライブでお会いいたしましょう！
Well then, let's meet at the membership-only Encore Live!
本日のお相手は私、儒烏風亭らでんでございました。
Your host for today was Juufuutei Raden.
それでは皆さん、良い夜をお過ごしください！
With that, I hope you all have a wonderful night!
さようならでん！
Sayonara-den!